(CELTIC FLUTE MUSIC PLAYING)
(BIRDSONG)
Where are you? Come out!
Come out! (LAUGHS)
Come on out.
(GIGGLES)
- I'm coming to get you.
- (GIGGLES)
Where are you, you little rascal?
I'm coming to get you.
Hm. (CHUCKLES)
Where is my little birthday girl, hm?
I'm going to gobble her up
when I find her.
- Oh! (LAUGHS)
- (SQUEALS)
I'm going to eat you. I am.
(MAKES MUNCHING NOISES)
Och, Fergus, no weapons on the table.
Can I shoot an arrow?
Can I? Can I? Can I? Can I?
Please? Can I? (LAUGHS)
- Not with that. Why not...
- (GIGGLES)
...use your very own?
- (GASPS)
- Happy birthday, my wee darling!
(BOW BEING PLUCKED)
- Now, there's a good girl.
- (STRAINS)
Draw all the way back now
to your cheek. That's right.
Keep both eyes open.
And, loose!
- I missed.
- Go and fetch it, then.
A bow, Fergus? She's a lady.
- Ooh! You!
- (LAUGHS)
(BIRDS CALLING)
(CREAKING)
(LONE BIRD CALLS)
(HEAVY BREATHING)
(HIGH-PITCHED CALL)
A will-o'-the-wisp.
(GROWLING)
They are real.
ELINOR:
Merida, come along, sweetheart.
- We're leaving now.
- MERIDA: I saw a wisp.
- I saw a wisp.
- A wisp?
You know, some say that
will-o'-the-wisps lead you to your fate.
- Oh, aye. Or an arrow.
- Och!
Come on, let's be off before we see
a dancing Tatty Bogle.
Or a giant having a jigger
in the bluebells.
Your father doesn't believe in magic.
Well, he should. Because it's true.
(GASPS)
(SCREAMS)
(GROWLS)
Mor'du! Elinor, run!
- (ROARS)
- Sire!
(YELLS)
(SNARLS)
Come on, you!
(ROARS)
MERIDA: Some say our destiny
is tied to the land...
...as much a part of us as we are of it.
Others say fate is woven together
like a cloth.
(THUNDER RUMBLES)
So that one's destiny intertwines
with many others.
It's the one thing we search for
or fight to change.
Some never find it.
But there are some who are led.
(YELLS)
The story of how my father lost his leg
to the demon bear Mor'du
became legend.
(GROANING)
I became a sister to three new brothers.
The princes.
Hamish, Hubert and Harris.
Wee devils, more like.
They get away with murder.
I can never get away with anything.
I'm the princess.
- Oh!
- (BAGPIPES PLAYING)
MERIDA: I'm the example.
(SLURPS)
I've got duties, responsibilities,
expectations.
My whole life is planned out,
preparing for the day I become...
Well, my mother.
She's in charge
of every single day of my life.
- (BAGPIPES CEASE)
- (SIGHS)
"Aye, Robin, Jolly Robin,
and thou shalt know of mine."
Project!
"And thou shalt know of mine!"
Enunciate. You must be understood
from anywhere in the room,
or it's all for naught.
- This is all for naught.
- I heard that!
- (SIGHS)
- From the top.
A princess must be knowledgeable
about her kingdom.
She does not doodle.
(PLAYS NOTES)
That's a C, dear.
- (SCREECHES)
- (SCREAMS)
(LAUGHS AND SNORTS)
A princess does not chortle.
- Mm!
- Does not stuff her gob!
Rises early.
- ...is compassionate...
- (CHICKEN SQUAWKS)
...patient, cautious,
clean.
And above all, a princess
strives for... Well, perfection.
MERIDA: But every once in a while,
there's a day
when I don't have to be a princess.
No lessons, no expectations.
A day where anything can happen.
A day I can change my fate.
Yah!
(LIVELY MUSIC PLAYING)
When cold wind is a' calling,
and the sky is clear and bright
Misty mountains sing and beckon,
lead me out into the light
I will ride, I will fly
Chase the wind and touch the sky
I will fly
Whoo-hoo!
(EAGLE CALLS)
Where dark woods hide secrets
and mountains are fierce and bold
Deep waters hold reflections
of times lost long ago
I will read every story,
take hold of my own dream
- Oh!
- (HORSE WHINNIES)
Be as strong as the seas are stormy
And proud as an eagle's scream
I will ride, I will fly
Chase the wind and touch the sky
I will fly
(SCREAMS EXCITEDLY)
And touch the sky
Whoo!
Chase the wind
Touch the sky
(WHINNIES)
I'm starving. You hungry too, Angus?
Pfft!
- Oats it is, then.
- (SNORTS)
Good day, Princess.
I cannot find the salt.
Where did you put it?
It was over there a minute ago,
the last time I looked at it.
And then, out of nowhere,
the biggest bear you've ever seen!
His hide littered with the weapons
of fallen warriors.
His face scarred with one dead eye.
I drew my sword and...
Whoosh!
One swipe, his sword shattered.
Then "chomp"! Dad's leg was clean off.
Down the monster's throat it went.
Oh, that's my favourite part.
Mor'du has never been seen since,
and is roaming the wilds
waiting his chance of revenge.
- (ROARING)
- Let him return.
I'll finish what I guddled in the first place.
Merida, a princess does not place
her weapons on the table.
Mum! It's just my bow.
A princess should not have weapons
in my opinion.
FERGUS: Leave her be.
Princess or not,
learning to fight is essential.
Mum?
You'll never guess what I did today.
- Hm?
- I climbed the Crone's Tooth,
and drank from the Fire Falls.
Fire Falls?
They say only the ancient kings
were brave enough to drink the fire.
(LAUGHS)
- What did you do, dear?
- Nothing, Mum.
Hungry, aren't we?
- Mum!
- You'll get dreadful collywobbles.
Oh, Fergus, will you look at
your daughter's plate?
- (DOGS BARKING)
- So what?
- Oh, you great...
- Don't let them lick... (SIGHS)
Boys, you're naughty.
Don't just play with your haggis.
- Urgh! (GAGGING)
- Och, how do you know you don't like it,
if you won't try it?
That's just a wee sheep's stomach.
It's delicious. Mm! (SMACKS LIPS)
- My lady.
- Thank you, Maudie.
FERGUS: You're getting too big,
the two of you.
ELINOR: Aha.
From the Lords Macintosh,
Mac Guffin and Dingwall.
Their responses, no doubt.
Aye, aye!
- FERGUS: Hey, hey! (LAUGHS)
- (MUNCHING LOUDLY)
Stay out of my food,
you greedy mongrels.
Chew on that, you manky dogs!
- (FERGUS LAUGHS)
- Fergus?
They've all accepted.
(DOGS SLOBBERING)
Who's accepted what, Mother?
Boys, you are excused.
(GIGGLING)
- Oof!
- (DOGS BARKING)
Hey! (LAUGHS)
What did I do now?
Your father has something
to discuss with you.
Fergus?
Oh. (CLEARS THROAT)
(COUGHS)
Er... Merida.
(SIGHS) The lords are presenting
their sons as suitors for your betrothal.
- What?
- The clans have accepted.
- Dad!
- What? (STAMMERS) I...
You... She... Elinor?
Honestly, Merida, I don't know why
you're reacting this way.
(SIGHS IN FRUSTRATION)
This year, each clan will present a suitor
to compete in the games for your hand.
I suppose a princess
just does what she's told?
A princess does not raise her voice.
Merida, this is what you've been
preparing for your whole life.
No, it's what you've been preparing
me for my whole life.
I won't go through with it.
You can't make me.
Merida!
Huh? Merida!
- Urgh!
- (DOGS BARKING)
Boys!
(GRUNTING)
Mother. Suitors? Marriage?
Once there was an ancient kingdom...
Oh, Mum!
Ancient kingdom.
Its name long forgotten,
ruled by a wise and fair king
who was much beloved.
And when he grew old he divided
the kingdom among his four sons,
that they should be the pillars
on which the peace of the land rested.
But the oldest prince
wanted to rule the land for himself.
He followed his own path
and the kingdom fell
to war, and chaos and ruin.
That's a nice story.
It's not just a story, Merida.
Legends are lessons.
They ring with truths.
Och, Mum.
I would advise you
to make your peace with this.
The clans are coming
to present their suitors.
- It's not fair.
- Och, Merida.
It's marriage.
It's not the end of the world.
(SIGHS IN DISBELIEF)
(ELINOR MUTTERING)
- FERGUS: You're muttering.
- I don't mutter.
Aye, you do. You mutter, lass,
when something's troubling you.
I blame you. Stubbornness.
It's entirely from your side of the family.
(LAUGHS)
I take it the talk didn't go too well, then?
Och, I don't know what to do.
- Speak to her, dear.
- I do speak to her.
- She just doesn't listen.
- Come on, now.
Pretend I'm Merida. Speak to me.
What would you say?
Och... I can't do this.
Sure you can.
There, there. That's my queen.
Right, here we go.
"I don't want to get married.
"I want to stay single
and let my hair flow in the wind
"as I ride through the glen
firing arrows into the sunset."
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
Merida, all this work,
all the time spent preparing you,
schooling you,
giving you everything we never had.
I ask you, what do you expect us to do?
Call off the gathering.
Would that kill them?
You're the queen.
You can just tell the lords
the princess is not ready for this.
In fact, she might not ever be ready
for this, so that's that.
Good day to you. We'll expect your
declarations of war in the morning.
I understand this must all seem unfair.
Even I had reservations
when I faced betrothal.
But we can't just run away
from who we are.
I don't want my life to be over.
I want my freedom!
But are you willing to pay the price
your freedom will cost?
I'm not doing any of this to hurt you.
If you could just try to see what I do,
I do out of love.
But it's my life, it's... (SIGHS)
I'm just not ready.
I think you'd see, if you could just...
I think I could make you understand
if you would just...
- ...listen.
(WHINNIES)
I swear, Angus,
this isn't going to happen.
Not if I have any say in it.
- (EXERTIVE GRUNTING)
- (DRUMS POUNDING)
(MEN STRAINING)
(DRUMS BEATING RHYTHMICALLY)
Mac Guffin!
MEN: Mac Guffin!
- Dingwall!
- MEN: Dingwall!
- Macintosh!
- MEN: Macintosh!
Ooh! Aah!
Oh.
(SIGHS)
(GRUNTS)
You look absolutely beautiful.
I can't breathe.
Och, shush! Give us a turn.
(GROANS) I can't move.
It's too tight.
- (STRAINS)
- It's perfect.
(GROANS)
(STRAINS)
- Merida?
- Mum?
Just...
Remember to smile.
(SNORING)
(PRINCES LAUGHING)
- (CONTINUES SNORING)
- Aye, they're coming.
Places, everyone. Places.
- (PEOPLE CLAMOURING)
- (DOGS BARKING)
Oh!
(PRINCES GRUNTING)
(FERGUS CHUCKLES)
I look fine, woman! Leave me be!
GUARD: My Lord!
I want to announce the arrival
of the lords...
- Ow!
- Who goes there? Who goes there?
(BAGPIPES PLAYING)
Boy!
(ALL CRY OUT)
(SHOUTING)
(SILENCE)
So, here we are... Er...
- ...the four clans.
- MAN: Aye.
- Er... Gathering...
- Oh.
- ...for...
- (DISCONTENTED MURMURS)
- ...the presentation of the suitors.
- (ALL CHEERING)
- FERGUS: Clan Macintosh.
MEN: Macintosh!
Your Majesty,
I present my heir and scion,
who defended our land
from the northern invaders,
and with his own sword, Stab Blooder,
vanquished 1,000 foes.
MEN: Macintosh!
- (SCOFFS)
- FERGUS: Clan Mac Guffin!
MEN: Mac Guffin!
Good Majesty, I present my eldest son,
who scuttled the Viking longships
and with his bare hands
vanquished 2,000 foes.
MEN: Mac Guffin!
Clan Dingwall.
MEN: Dingwall!
I present my only son
who was besieged by 10,000 Romans
and he took out a whole armada
singlehandedly.
With one arm, he was...
With one arm he was steering the ship
and with the other
he held his mighty sword
and struck down a whole attacking fleet.
- MAN: Lies!
- What? I heard that.
- (MEN SNICKERING)
- Go on. Say it to my face.
Or are ye scared, simpering jackanapes,
afraid to muss your pretty hair?
- At least we have hair.
- And all our teeth.
(SPEAKS IN THICK ACCENT)
- MAN: Huh?
- (SHEEP BLEATS)
And we don't hide under bridges,
you grumpy old troll.
(ALL LAUGHING)
You want to laugh, huh?
Wee Dingwall!
(SCREAMS) Get off me!
(LAUGHING)
(PLAYING LIVELY TUNE)
(GROANING)
(SCREAMS)
(YELPS)
Nut 'em! Nut 'em! That's the way to...
All right.
Shut it!
(MUSIC WINDS DOWN)
Now, that's all done.
You've had your go at each other.
Show a little decorum.
And no more fighting.
- (MACE CLANGING)
- (SCREAMS)
(LIVELY TUNE CONTINUES)
(YELLING)
(BATTLE CRY)
Ow!
(GROANS)
(SHEEP BLEATS)
(YELLS)
FERGUS: You want a fresh one?
(MUSIC STOPS)
(CLAN CHIEFS WHINING IN PAIN)
FERGUS: Crivens, you're fierce.
I didn't start it. It was...
My lady Queen, I feel terrible.
My humblest apologies.
- We mean no disrespect.
- I'm sorry, love, I didn't... But...
- Yes, dear.
- (CLEARS THROAT)
Now, where were we?
Ah, yes. In accordance with our laws,
by the rights of our heritage,
only the firstborn of each
of the great leaders
- may be presented as champion.
- Firstborn?
And thus compete for the hand
of the Princess of Dun Broch.
To win the fair maiden
they must prove their worth
by feats of strength or arms
in the games.
It is customary that the challenge
be determined by the princess herself.
Archery! Archery.
(ALL MURMURING)
I choose archery.
- Let the games begin!
- (ALL CHEERING)
(GRUNTING)
(YELLS)
(SCREAMS)
(GRUNTING)
Pull!
- Pull!
- (MEN CRYING OUT IN SURPRISE)
(LIVELY BAGPIPES PLAYING)
- (MAN ROARING)
- (CHILDREN SCREAMING)
(MOOING AND BARKING)
- I'll just take one.
- Ooh!
PRINCE: Ooh!
Oh!
Now, I have told you,
you're not allowed... Oh!
- Oh!
- Argh!
- (PRINCES GIGGLING)
- Oh!
(SHEEP BLEATING)
(HORN SOUNDING)
(DOGS HOWL)
(CROWD CHEERING)
It's time!
- Archers, to your marks!
- Aye, archers, to your marks.
And may the lucky arrow find its target.
(FERGUS CHUCKLES)
(EXCITED SQUEALING)
Oi! Get on with it.
CROWD: Ooh. (LAUGHS)
(GROANS)
- Och!
- I bet he wishes he was tossing cabers.
- Or holding up bridges. (LAUGHS)
- Shh!
(GIRLS SQUEAL)
CROWD: Aw...
(YELLS ANGRILY)
At least you hit the target, son.
(CONTINUES YELLING)
Oh, that's attractive.
(CONTINUES WAILING)
- MAN: I got it!
- Good arm.
And such lovely flowing locks.
- Fergus.
- What?
(LAUGHTER)
(GASPS)
Oh, wee lamb.
Oh, come on! Shoot, boy!
- (CROWD CHEERING)
- (LAUGHS IN TRIUMPH)
Well done, lad! Well done.
(STARTS SINGING)
- Feast your eyes!
- (CHIEFS SCREAM)
- That's my boy. (LAUGHS)
- (GAGGING)
Well, that's just grand now, isn't it?
- Guess who's coming to dinner?
- Fergus.
By the way, hope you don't mind
being called Lady Ding...
(WHINES)
- (CROWD GASPS)
- I am Merida.
Firstborn descendant
of Clan Dun Broch.
And I'll be shooting for my own hand.
- Oh!
- (CROWD MURMURING)
What are you doing?
Merida!
Curse this dress!
(SHOCKED GASPS)
(CROWD GASPS IN AWE)
Merida, stop this!
Don't you dare loose another arrow.
(EXHALES)
Merida, I forbid it.
Michty me!
I've just about had enough of you, lass!
- You're the one that wants me to...
- You embarrassed them.
- You embarrassed me.
- I followed the rules.
You don't know what you've done!
- Just don't care how I...
- It'll be fire and sword if it's not set right.
- Just listen!
- I am the Queen!
You listen to me!
Ugh! This is so unfair!
Ha! Unfair?
You're never there for me.
This whole marriage is what you want.
Do you ever bother
to ask what I want? No.
You walk around telling me what to do,
what not to do,
trying to make me be like you.
Well, I'm not going to be like you.
Oh, you're acting like a child.
And you're a beast.
- That's what you are!
- Oh, Merida.
- I'll never be like you.
- No, stop that!
- I'd rather die than be like you!
- (GASPS)
Merida, you are a princess,
- and I expect you to act like one.
- Mum!
Oh!
(WEEPS)
ELINOR: Merida!
Merida!
Oh, dear.
Ah!
Oh, no. What have I done?
Oh.
(SOBBING)
Oh! Oh! Oh!
(WHINNIES)
Whoa!
(SOBS) Angus!
(WHINNIES AND SNORTS)
(ANGUS WHINNIES)
(WISP CALLS)
- (WHISPERS) Come on, Angus.
- (ANGUS NICKERS)
Angus!
(NICKERS)
(SIGHS)
(WISPS CALL)
(ANGUS NEIGHS)
(WISP CALLS)
(WHINNYING)
Why would the wisps lead me here?
(BELL TINKLES)
Uh...
(WOOD GENTLY TAPPING)
Oh, look around.
You holler if you see anything you like.
Everything is half off.
Uh...
- Who are you?
- Just a humble woodcarver.
Um...
I don't understand... (GASPS)
- See anything you like?
- Uh...
Perhaps a touch of whimsy
to brighten any dank chamber?
But the will-o'-the-wisps, they...
Oh! This is one of a kind!
I'll make you a deal for this rare prize.
- Your broom!
- Oh! (SNAPS)
- It was sweeping by itself.
- That's ridiculous.
Wood cannot be imbued
with magical properties.
I should know. I'm a wit... Whittler.
Of wood.
Oh, how about this conversation starter?
It's made of yew wood.
- (GENTLE CLATTERING)
- Tough as stone.
Oh, ah, ah, ah, ah!
That's stuffed. (LAUGHS)
- Staring is rude.
- (GASPS) Ooh! The crow's talking!
That's not all I can do.
La-la la-la la-la
- (SINGS HIGH NOTES)
- (SNAPS)
(SQUAWKS)
- You're a witch!
- Woodcarver.
That's why the wisps led me here.
- Woodcarver!
- You'll change my fate!
- You see, it's my mother.
I'm not a witch!
Too many unsatisfied customers.
If you're not going to buy anything,
get out. (SNAPS)
- No! The wisps led me here!
- I don't care!
- Get out! Shoo! Get! Be gone with you!
- I'll buy it all.
- What? What was that?
- Every carving.
Well... (STAMMERING)
(LAUGHS) And how are you going
to pay for that, sweetie?
- With this.
- W...
Oh, my, that's lovely, that is.
That would set us up for months.
(CLATTERING)
- MERIDA: Ah, ah, ah.
- (GASPS)
- Every carving and one spell.
- (SQUAWKS)
Are you sure
you know what you're doing?
I want a spell to change my mum.
That'll change my fate.
Hmm... Done!
- (CHUCKLES)
- Where are you going?
(SNAPS)
- (SQUAWKING)
- There.
What are you doing?
You never conjure where you carve.
Very important.
WITCH: The last time I did this
was for a prince.
- (CLAPS)
- (CAULDRON IGNITES)
Easy on the eyes. Tight pants.
He demanded I give him
the strength of ten men.
And he gave me this for a spell.
A spell that would change his fate.
And did he get what he was after?
(LAUGHS) Yes.
And made off with an especially
attractive mahogany cheese board.
Now, what do I need? Oh!
- Just a little bit of this.
- (THUNDER RUMBLING)
Ah. (CHUCKLES)
Hoo!
(SQUAWKING)
Tee-tee-tee-tee. Whoosh.
That'll do.
(HUMS HAPPILY)
- (SQUAWKS)
- Mi-mi-mi-mi-mi-mi-mi.
(BANG)
(PANICKED WHINNYING)
And now let's see. What have we here?
(GASPS) Oh!
- Hey!
- (SQUAWKS)
Uh, a cake?
- You don't want it?
- Yes! I want it.
You're sure if I give this to my mum,
it will change my fate?
Oh. (CHUCKLES)
Trust me. It'll do the trick, dearie.
Expect delivery of your purchase
within a fortnight.
Ooh! Ooh...
What was that thing about the spell?
Did you say something about
the spell?
Mor'du, Mor'du, now the time has
come for all of us to slaughter you
ALL: Hooray!
Mor'du, Mor'du...
(DISTANT SINGING)
- ELINOR: Merida.
- Mum!
Ooh, uh... I, uh...
- Oh, I've been worried sick.
- You... You were?
I didn't know where you'd gone
or when you'd come back.
I didn't know what to think.
Oh, look at your dress.
Oh. Angus threw me. But I'm not hurt.
Well, you're home now,
so that's the end of it.
- Honestly?
- I've pacified the lords for now.
Your father's out there
"entertaining" them.
Come taste my blade, you manky bear
For gobbling up my leg
I'll hunt you, then I'll skin you,
hang your noggin on a peg...
(CHEERING)
Of course, we both know
a decision still has to be made.
- What's this?
- It's a peace offering.
I made it. For you. Special.
You made this for me?
Mm.
Oh. Interesting flavour.
- How do you feel?
- What... What is that?
- Different?
- Mm...
Tart and, um, (GULPS) gamy.
Have you changed your mind at all
about the marriage and all that?
Oh, that's better.
Now, why don't we go
upstairs to the lords
and put this whole kerfuffle to rest?
Hm?
(CELTIC FLUTE MUSIC PLAYING)
Ooh.
- Mother?
- I'm woozy suddenly.
My head's spinning like a top. Ooh!
- Mum!
- Oh, suddenly I'm not so well.
Er... How... How do you feel
about the marriage now?
Merida! Oh, just take me to my room.
FERGUS: All right, that's fine.
That's just fine.
A little to the left. That's good.
A wee bit to the left. That's good.
It's good enough.
Now, clear out of there, boys.
I don't want you to spoil my shot.
- What? (CLEARS THROAT)
- My lady Queen.
We've been waiting patiently.
Milords, I am out of sorts
at the moment.
But you shall have your answer.
(BURPS)
- Oh!
- Eh?
Presently.
Now, if you'll (GROANS) excuse us.
- (ALL CHEERING)
- FERGUS: Elinor, look!
It's Mor'du! (LAUGHS)
Elinor? Are you all right, dear?
Fine. I'm fine.
Go about avenging your leg. Oh...
Aye. You heard her, lads.
I dream about the perfect way
to make this devil die.
(ALL CHEERING)
Just take all the time you need
to getting yourself right, Mum.
Then maybe in a bit you might have
something new to say on the marriage.
What was in that cake?
(SCOFFS) Cake.
(COUGHS)
(GROANS)
Mum?
So I'll just tell them
the wedding's off, then?
(ELINOR GROANING)
Mum?
(DEEP GROANING)
(GASPS)
(SCREAMS)
(LOW GROWLING)
Bear!
(WHINES)
(FRIGHTENED GROWL)
(PANTING)
- (GROWLS)
- (SCREAMS)
(SURPRISED ROARING)
- (GROANS)
- Oh!
Mum?
You're... You're a bear!
(GROANS)
Why a bear?
Oh, that scaffy witch
gave me a gammy spell.
It's not my fault.
I didn't ask her
to change you into a bear.
I just wanted her to change you.
(ROARS)
(ALL CHEERING)
- Shh. Did you hear that? (SNIFFS)
- (MUSIC STOPS)
Something's not right.
(ANXIOUS WHINING)
There's no point in having a go at me.
The witch is to blame.
Goggly old hag.
Eyes all over the place.
- Unbelievable.
- (GROANING)
- I'll get her to fix this.
- (SIGHS)
MERIDA: Why do I always get blamed
for everything? It's just not fair.
(SNIFFING)
Everybody, follow me.
And keep a sharp eye.
Here we go.
Another hunt through the castle.
But we haven't had dessert yet.
(SPEAKS IN THICK ACCENT)
(LAUGHS) I have no idea.
MERIDA: Mum, you can't go out there.
Mum! Wait!
What are you doing?
Dad. The Bear King?
If he so much as sees you, you're dead.
LORD DINGWALL: Another one of
your entertainments to bore us to death!
LORD MACINTOSH:
Oh, and what exactly are we after...
Mum!
LORD MACINTOSH: ...my liege?
LORD MACGUFFIN:
Best to humour him.
He is, after all, the King.
(SNIFFING)
He's like a hound with that nose of his.
(LICKS AND SPITS)
Mum, wait.
- We have to...
- (GROANS)
- (CLATTERING)
- Follow me.
Stop.
Stop!
(GASPS)
You're covered with fur.
You're not naked.
It's not like anyone's gonna see you.
(SCREAMS)
Now you've done it.
Maudie!
- (STUTTERING)
- Just calm down, lass. What is it?
- Spit it out, Maudie!
(SHOUTING) A bear!
I knew it! (YELLS)
(ALL SHOUTING)
Would you just listen to me?
- We can't go this way. You'll be seen.
- (MEN YELLING)
Quick! This way!
Mum?
(WHIMPERS)
(ALL GASP)
(SOFTLY) Mum? Oh!
(MEN SHOUTING)
- Oh!
- (ELINOR WHINING)
Hm?
A witch turned Mum into a bear.
It's not my fault.
We've got to get out of the castle.
I need your help.
Oh, all right.
You can have my desserts
for two... Three weeks.
Okay. Fine. A year.
- Did you hear that?
- Shh.
(ECHOING ROAR)
- There it goes!
- (MEN SHOUTING)
- (MOCK ROARING CONTINUES)
- FERGUS: Come on, lads!
(YELLS)
- (YELLS)
- (MOCK GROWLING)
There it goes!
(ALL YELLING)
(BIRD CALL)
- Come on, Mum.
- (WHINES)
(CLATTERING)
LORD MACGUFFIN:
Think we should lay a trap?
FERGUS: Try shutting yours!
(ALL ARGUING)
(MOCK GROWLING)
- There he is!
- (MEN SHOUTING)
(ALL SHOUTING)
FERGUS: I'm sure it went this way.
LORD MACGUFFIN:
You can see my house from here.
It must have sprouted wings.
Was carried away by a giant birdy.
- A dragon, perhaps.
- Bear in the castle!
Doesn't make sense.
It cannot open doors.
He's got big giant paws!
Let's just get inside.
(GRUNTING)
- It's locked.
- Dingwall was the last up.
LORD DINGWALL:
I propped it open with a stick.
(MEN GRUMBLING)
HANDMAID: What did you see, Maudie?
Just spit it out, Maudie.
Oh, for goodness' sakes, Maudie,
would you get a grip?
(CLATTERING)
(SCREAMS)
HANDMAID: Maudie, honey, come here!
It's all right!
Come on, Mum. Quick.
(GROANS)
Shh.
(CRASHING AND CLATTERING)
(CLATTERING)
(GIGGLING)
(SNEEZES)
(WHINES)
They'll be fine. Won't you, boys?
(SNIFFS)
Mum, we've got to hurry.
Now, I'll be back soon.
Go on and help yourself
to anything you want, as a reward.
(ALL GASP)
(STRAINING) Oh!
(LORD DINGWALL SIGHS)
Right!
MERIDA: Where are these wisps?
Come out, wisps. Come on out.
Lead me to the witch's cottage.
I'm here!
Fine. Don't come out
now that my mum's watching.
(WHINES)
I was standing right here
and the wisp appeared right there.
Then a whole trail of them
led me off into the forest.
Oh, does she think we're just going
to happen upon the witch's cottage?
(OWLS HOOTING)
(DISTANT HOWLING)
Oh, Mum, I know this place.
The witch's cottage...
It's this way! Come on! Hurry!
I can't believe it. I found it.
(WHINES)
No. She was here.
No, really, she was just here.
(WHINES)
Oh, wait.
- No.
- (BANGS DOOR SHUT)
No, no. No! No!
- (METAL RATTLES)
- Oh.
(RUMBLING)
(DINGING)
(SHRIEKS)
(BUBBLING)
Welcome to the Crafty Carver,
home of bear-themed carvings
and novelties.
I am completely out of stock at this time.
But if you'd like to enquire about
portraits or wedding cake toppers,
pour vial one into the cauldron.
If you'd like the menu in Gaelic, vial two.
If you're that red-haired lass, vial three.
To speak with a live homunculus...
Princess, I'm off to the Wickerman
Festival in Stornoway
and won't be back till spring.
There's one bit I forgot to tell you
about the spell.
By the second sunrise,
your spell will be permanent,
- (GASPS)
- unless you remember these words.
Fate be changed,
look inside,
mend the bond
torn by pride.
"Fate be changed... Mend the bond."
What does that mean?
One more time.
Fate be changed,
look inside,
mend the bond
torn by pride.
That's it. Ta-ta.
Oh, and thank you for shopping
at the Crafty Carver.
No. No! Where'd you go?
- Welcome to the Crafty Carver...
- What?
...for all your...
(SPEECH OVERLAPPING)
Maybe there's a book of spells.
Look around. We'll need more vials.
I'm off to the Wickerman Festival
in Stornoway...
(SCRAMBLED MESSAGES)
Thank you for visiting.
Have a lovely day.
(BANG)
(WHINES SOFTLY)
(RAIN PATTERING)
(MERIDA STRAINING)
(ELINOR SIGHS)
We'll sort it out tomorrow.
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
(FAINT SINGING)
(ELINOR SINGING IN GAELIC)
- (CRACK OF THUNDER)
- (SCREAMS)
Oh. (SPEAKS GAELIC)
My brave wee lassie, I'm here.
I'll always be right here.
(CONTINUES SINGING IN GAELIC)
(BOTH SINGING)
(BIRDSONG)
Uh... Good morning.
(MOANS)
So... (CHUCKLES)
- What's all this supposed to be?
- (SIGHS)
Oh.
(MOANS AND GRUNTS)
What?
(HUFFS AND SNORTS)
Sorry. I don't speak bear.
(HUFFS)
Oh.
(MOANS)
Ah!
(GRUNTS IN SURPRISE)
(SLURPS)
- Find those by the creek, did you?
- Mm-hm.
They're nightshade berries.
Mmm.
They're poisonous.
(SPUTTERING)
Where did you get this water?
It has worms.
(GULPS)
(THUDDING)
(BIRDS SQUAWK)
- (GIGGLES) Come on.
- (GROWLS SOFTLY)
Breakfast.
(GRUNTS APPROVINGLY)
Oh, wait. A princess should not
have weapons, in your opinion.
Uh-huh... (GROANS)
There you go.
Go on.
(GROANS)
How do you know you don't like it
if you won't try it?
(WHINES)
(GROANS APPROVINGLY)
Mm.
(MUNCHING LOUDLY)
(GRUNTS)
(BURPS)
(GROANS)
(SLOW SONG PLAYING)
This love it is a distant star
Guiding us home wherever we are
This love it is a burning sun
Shining light on the things
that we've done
I tried to speak to you every day
But each word we spoke
the wind blew away
How did we let it come to this?
What we just tasted...
(MERIDA LAUGHS)
How will it feel when this day is done?
And can we keep
what we've only begun?
(CRIES OUT)
Could these walls
come crumbling down?
I want to feel my feet on the ground
Can we carry this love that we share
Into the open air
Hey!
Where are you going?
This love it is a burning sun
Mum, come back.
(GROWLS)
- Uh...
- (SNARLS)
- Oh...
- (GROWLING)
Mum, is that you?
(ROARS)
Uh... Mum?
(WHINES)
You changed.
Like you were a...
I mean, like you were a bear
on the inside.
(WHINES AND SNORTS)
(WISP CALLS)
A wisp.
- Mum!
- (WISP SQUEAKS)
Stop it!
Mum, no!
(WISP CALLING)
Mum...
(GRUNTS)
- (GROANS)
- Jings, crivens, help ma boab.
Mum, I know you're scared,
you're tired, you don't understand,
but we've got to keep our heads.
Just calm down.
Listen.
(FAINT WHISPERING)
(FAINT WHISPERING CONTINUES)
(WISP CALLS)
They'll show us the way.
(WISPS CALLING)
(WISP CALLING)
MERIDA: Mum, look.
(WIND WHISTLES)
(ELINOR BEAR GROANS)
MERIDA: Why did the wisps
bring us here?
(ELINOR BEAR MOANS)
(ELINOR BEAR HUFFS AND SNORTS)
Whoever they were,
they've been gone for a long, long time.
(SCREAMS)
(GROANS)
- (WHINES)
- I'm fine, Mum.
Just fine.
It's, uh,
a throne room.
You suppose this could've
been the kingdom
in that story you were telling me?
- (MOANS)
- The one with the princes.
(GROANS)
One,
two,
three,
four.
The oldest.
(GROANS)
Split, like the tapestry.
(GROWLING)
(GASPS)
The spell. It's happened before.
"Strength of ten men."
"Fate be changed."
"Changed his fate."
Oh, no.
The prince became...
(GROWLING)
- Mor'du.
- (ROARS)
(ROARING)
(SCREAMS)
(GROANING)
- (ROARS)
- (FABRIC TEARING)
- (WHIMPERING)
- (ROARS)
(SNARLS)
(MOANS)
(HUFFING AND PANTING)
(SCREAMS)
(CREAKING)
(MERIDA GROANS)
Mum, we need to get back to the castle.
If we don't hurry,
you'll become like Mor'du.
A bear!
A real bear. Forever!
- (WHINES)
- "Mend the bond torn by pride."
The witch gave us the answer.
The tapestry.
- (ELINOR GRUMBLES)
- Mum, do you have a better idea?
(GRUNTS)
(STRAINING)
That'll do.
(TALKING INDISTINCTLY)
(MEN SHOUTING)
No more talk. No more traditions.
We settle this now!
You're the King.
You decide which one of our sons
your daughter will marry.
None of your sons
are fit to marry my daughter.
Then our alliance is over!
This means war!
(SHOUTING)
They're gonna murder each other.
You've got to stop them
before it's too late.
(WHINES)
I know, I know!
But how do we get you through there
and up to the tapestry
with the lot of them
boiling over like that?
- (GRUNTS)
- Oh!
(SHOUTING)
(SHOUTING STOPS)
- What are you doing, lass?
- It's all right, Dad.
(CLEARS THROAT) I, um...
I have...
Well, you see, I...
I have been in conference
with the Queen.
- Is that so?
- Aye, it is.
- Well, where is she, then?
- She, uh...
How do we know that
this isn't some trick?
- I'd never...
- This is highly irregular.
- What are you playing at?
- Where is the Queen?
LORD MACINTOSH: We will not stand
for any more of this jiggery-pokery.
- That's right. Let's see her.
- Shut it!
(SILENCE)
(LAUGHS)
(CLEARS THROAT)
Well, I, uh...
Uh...
Once there was an ancient kingdom.
What is this?
That kingdom fell into war
and chaos and ruin...
Och, we've all heard that tale.
Lost kingdom.
Aye, but it's true.
I know now how one selfish act
can turn the fate of a kingdom.
LORD MACGUFFIN:
Bah, it's just a legend.
Legends are lessons.
They ring with truths.
Our kingdom is young.
Our stories are not yet legend.
But in them, our bond was struck.
Our clans were once enemies.
But when invaders threatened us
from the sea,
you joined together to defend our lands.
You fought for each other.
You risked everything for each other.
Lord Mac Guffin, my dad saved your life,
stopping an arrow
as you ran to Dingwall's aid.
Aye, and I'll never forget it.
MERIDA: And, Lord Macintosh,
you saved my dad
when you charged in on heavy horse
and held off the advance.
And we all know how Lord Dingwall
broke the enemy line.
With a mighty throw of his spear!
I was aiming at you, you big tumshie.
(ALL LAUGH)
The story of this kingdom
is a powerful one.
My dad rallied your forces
and you made him your king.
It was an alliance forged in bravery
and friendship
and it lives to this day.
(ALL CHEERING)
But I've been selfish.
I tore a great rift in our kingdom.
There's no one to blame but me.
And I know now
that I need to amend my mistake
and mend our bond.
And so, there is the matter
of my betrothal.
I've decided to do what's right
and...
...and...
...break tradition.
(GASPING AND MUTTERING)
My mother...
...the Queen, feels...
...uh, in her heart
that I...
...that we be free to...
...write our own story...
...follow our hearts
and find love in our own time.
- That's (SNIFFS) beautiful.
- (ALL SNIFFLING)
The Queen and I put the decision
to you, my lords.
Might our young people decide
for themselves who they will love?
Huh?
Well, since you've obviously
made up your minds about this,
I have one thing to say.
- This is...
- A grand idea!
Give us our own say
in choosing our fate.
- What?
- Aye. Why shouldn't we choose?
But she's the princess.
I did not pick her out. It was your idea.
And you... You feel the same way?
(SPEAKS UNINTELLIGIBLY)
- Good?
- (GRUNTS)
(GIGGLES)
Well, that settles it.
Let these lads try and win her heart
before they win her hand.
If they can.
I say, the wee Dingwall
has a fighting chance.
Fine, then. Seems for once we agree.
- It was my idea in the first place.
- (ALL LAUGHING)
(SIGHS)
(ALL MUTTERING CONTENTEDLY)
Just like your mum.
You devil.
(GASPS)
Uh... Everyone to the cellar!
Let's crack open the King's
private reserve to celebrate!
(ALL CHEERING)
Oh.
(LAUGHS) Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Psst. Bring the tiny glasses.
(TALKING AND LAUGHING)
(SIGHS)
(MERIDA GIGGLES)
(SINGS HAPPILY)
Oh, the tapestry!
Mend the bond...
Mend the bond.
Stitch it up. This'll change you back.
We just need needle and thread.
(GRUNTS)
(GROWLS)
- Mum?
- (SNARLS)
Mum? Not now.
No. Please, not now.
(SNIFFING)
- Mum...
- (MEN LAUGHING)
- (GROWLS)
- Shh.
(SINGING JOVIALLY)
Elinor, dear, you'll never guess
who just solved our little suitor problem.
- (THUNDER RUMBLING)
- (FERGUS BREATHING HEAVILY)
Elinor!
It can't be true!
Elinor, answer me, lass!
Elinor!
- Merida.
- (SNARLING)
- What?
- Dad, no! It's not what you think.
- Merida, get back!
- No!
(GROWLING)
(YELLING)
No, Dad! Don't hurt her!
- Get out of here!
- (SCREAMS)
Merida! No!
(ROARS)
(YELLS)
- No!
- (ROARS)
(MOANS)
(GROANING)
- Mum.
- (WHINES)
(WHIMPERS)
It's all right. I'm all right. It's nothing.
It's just a little scratch. Mum!
- My liege!
- (ALL LAUGHING)
Fergus.
- Bear!
- (MOANING)
- (GROANS)
- Dad!
Count your stars, lass.
It almost had you. Are you hurt?
It's your wife, Elinor.
- (ELINOR WHINING)
- (MEN SHOUTING)
Close the gate!
- You're talking nonsense!
- It's the truth!
There was a witch and she
gave me a spell. It's not Mor'du.
Mor'du or not, I'll avenge your mother!
- I'll not risk losing you, too.
- MERIDA: No, Dad! Just listen to me.
Listen! You can't!
- It's your wife Elinor!
- Maudie, keep this and don't let her out.
- What about the bear?
- Just stay put.
(BARKING)
Oh...
(YELLING)
(GRUNTING)
(STRAINING)
(FRUSTRATED GRUNT)
Come on, you sorry bunch of galoots!
Yah!
Mum!
No.
No. Mum.
(WEEPING)
(GROANING)
Maudie. Maudie!
I need you!
Now!
(MERIDA GASPS) Oh, no.
Maudie.
(GASPS)
Get the key.
(GROWLING)
(SCREAMING)
Yah!
Oh, Maudie!
(SCREAMING)
(BOTH SCREAMING)
Needle and thread. Needle and thread.
Needle and thread.
(BARKING)
(HUFFING AND GASPING)
(GRUNTS AND MOANS)
There he goes!
Needle and thread.
Needle and thread. Needle and thread.
Ah, you beauty!
(GASPS)
(STRAINING)
(SHRIEKS)
(GASPS)
(WHIMPERING)
One, two... Huh?
(GASPS)
- (THUD)
- MAUDIE: Oh!
(CUB GROWLING)
(GASPS)
(WHINING)
(CRIES OUT)
Steady, Hamish.
FERGUS: There he goes.
- (GRUNTS)
- (DOGS BARKING)
(GROANS)
(MEN SHOUTING IN DISTANCE)
FERGUS: We've got his track!
- (BARKING)
- (MOANS)
- Back, back, back!
- Get him!
(GROANS)
Angus! Easy, laddie.
(CRIES OUT)
Hubert, Harris, help Hamish.
(SHOUTING)
FERGUS: Watch your blade!
You're going to take somebody's arm off!
Aye, we've got you now!
- FERGUS: Give me a hand over here!
- Put your back into it, Dingwall!
LORD DINGWALL:
I'm doing all the pulling here.
LORD MACGUFFIN:
Down you go, you scoundrel.
(SQUEALS) Done!
(WISP CALLS)
(HIGH-PITCHED CALLS)
Yah!
(GROWLS)
- (ELINOR BEAR GROANS)
- (MEN SHOUTING)
(DOGS BARKING)
- Hah!
- (WHIMPERS)
(GROWLS)
(YELLS)
(GROANS)
(MEN GASP IN SHOCK)
- Get back. That's my mother.
- Are you out of your mind, lass?
- Mum, are you hurt?
- (MOANS)
(GRUNTS)
(CRIES OUT)
(YELLS)
Merida!
- (FERGUS GROANS)
- I'll not let you kill my mother.
- (FERGUS SCREAMS)
- Boys!
(SCREAMING)
Boys?
(HEAVY THUD)
(GROWLS)
- Mor'du!
- Kill it!
- (ALL YELLING)
- (ROARS)
(MEN SCREAMING)
You scoundrel!
(MEN GROANING)
(ROARS)
Come on!
I'll take you with my bare hands!
(FERGUS GROANS)
(FERGUS CRIES OUT)
(ROARS)
(WHIMPERING)
(SNARLS)
(SCREAMS)
(ROARS)
(ELINOR BEAR MOANS)
(BOTH ROARING)
Mum!
(GROANS)
(BOTH SNARLING)
(ELINOR CRIES OUT IN PAIN)
(STONE CRACKING)
(MERIDA SCREAMS)
(ROARING)
(CRACKING AND CRUMBLING)
(ROARS FEROCIOUSLY)
(SHRIEKS)
(GASPS)
(GASPS) The second sunrise.
(STRAINING)
(GRUNTS)
(WHIMPERS)
(WHINES)
No...
I don't understand. I...
(SNIFFLING)
(WEEPING)
Oh, Mum, I'm sorry.
This is all my fault.
I did this to you.
To us.
(SNIFFING)
You've always been there for me.
You've never given up on me.
I just want you back.
(MERIDA SOBS)
I want you back, Mummy.
I love you.
(GASPS)
(LAUGHS)
Mum! You're back!
(LAUGHING TEARFULLY)
You changed!
Oh, darling,
we both have.
Elinor!
Oh, oh, oh!
(ALL LAUGHING)
Elinor! Oh!
Ah!
Er... Urgh!
Oh, dear.
You're back. She came back to us.
It's a great day for this kingdom.
The curse is broke.
Oh! Mum.
Ooh. Erm... Dear?
- Eh?
- I'm naked.
Naked as a wee babby.
Don't just stare at me. Do something!
What the... Avert your eyes, lads!
Show some respect!
(ALL MUTTERING AWKWARDLY)
(PRINCES LAUGH)
Now that's what I call
a wee naked babby!
(LAUGHING)
Merida, Elinor, hurry up.
They're leaving.
- Mum!
- They're off! Come on!
We've got to wave them off!
Come along!
(MUSIC PLAYING)
Though I may speak
some tongue of old
Or even spit out some holy word
(PRINCES SQUEALING)
I have no strength with which to speak
Oof! (SCREAMS)
When you sit me down
and see I'm weak
(TALKING AND LAUGHING)
Goodbye! All the best!
Fair wind to your sails!
We will run and scream
You will dance with me
But how did this... (GROANS)
(BARKING)
MERIDA: There are those who say fate
is something beyond our command,
that destiny is not our own.
But I know better.
Our fate lives within us.
You only have to be brave enough
to see it.
(WISP LAUGHS)
We will run and scream
You will dance with me
We'll fulfil our dreams
and we'll be free
We will be who we are
And then heal our scars
Sadness will be far away
So I had done wrong
But you put me right
My judgement burned
in the black of night
When I give less than I take
It is my fault, my own mistake
We will run and scream
You will dance with me
We'll fulfil our dreams
and we'll be free
We will be who we are
And then heal our scars
Sadness will be far away
(SNORING)
(BIRD CAWS)
(SHEEP BLEATING)
Delivery. Sign here, sign here.
(CAWS)
Come on, birdbrain. I haven't got all day.